{"tossups": [{"question": "This country was saved by the arrival of Anton von L\u2019Estocq\u2019s forces during a battle in which 11,000 enemy cavalry charged through a heavy snowstorm. This country\u2019s troops crossed the Alle River in an attempt to defeat Jean Lannes before aid arrived; however, that assault backfired on the Count of Bennigsen, and this country was forced to sign the Treaty of Tilsit. The loser at the Battles of Eylau and Friedland was, for ten points, what country whose refusal to follow the Continental System prompted a French invasion in 1812?", "answer": "<b> Russia</b>n Empire", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "This state\u2019s Camp Jackson riot and subsequent massacre was triggered by Nathaniel Lyon\u2019s arrest of the state militia. That massacre led to the brief Price-Harney Truce between the federal government and this state\u2019s government, which ultimately collapsed at the Battle of Wilson\u2019s Creek near Springfield. Many people from this state fought as guerrilla bushwhackers, often against Jayhawkers in a neighboring state. For ten points, name this state in the Civil War whose \u201cBorder Ruffians\u201d rushed in to fight in \u201cBleeding Kansas.\u201d", "answer": "<b> Missouri</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "A thinker from this philosophical movement thought that \u201cWhat\u2019s a mistake but a kind of take?\u201d was one of the secrets of the universe after inhaling too much nitrous oxide. The author of<em> Making It Explicit</em>, Robert Brandom, is considered a revivalist of this philosophical school with his teacher, Richard Rorty. A book titled for this philosophical school is subtitled \u201cA New Name for Some Old Ways of Thinking.\u201d For ten points, name this American philosophical movement that included C.S. Peirce [PURSE], John Dewey, and William James.", "answer": "<b> pragmatism</b>", "metadata": "Philosophy - Philosophy"}, {}, {"question": "The earliest examples of this form include Jacopo Peri\u2019s<em> Dafne</em> and the oldest one still performed,<em> The Coronation of</em> <em>Poppea</em> by Claudio Monteverdi. Rival types of this art form in the 18th century included<em> seria</em> and<em> buffa</em>; examples of the latter include<em> The Barber of Seville</em>. A librettist writes the words for, for ten points, what art form that combines theatrical staging and, usually, classical music?", "answer": "<b> opera</b> (prompt on music; prompt on theater)", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Other Fine Arts - Misc Arts"}, {}, {"question": "One of this religion\u2019s scriptures is called the Holy Piby. This religion celebrates a 1966 plane landing at Palisadoes Airport with its Grounation Day holiday. This religion is divided into denominations like Nyahbinghi called \u201cMansions\u201d and keeps a diet caled Ital [EYE-tall]. For ten points, name this religion which regards Haile Selassie as the second coming of Christ, a Jamaican movement famous for its practitioners\u2019 dreadlocks and cannabis use.", "answer": "<b> Rasta</b>farianism (accept word forms, including<b> Rastafari</b>))", "metadata": "Religion - Religion"}, {"question": "A Bible used in this event is maintained by St. John\u2019s Lodge. The central figure of this event arrived by barge to Murray\u2019s Wharf and, after it, was forced to walk to his residence at Franklin House since too many people were crowding the streets. Robert Livingston administered an oath to the subject of this event, who allegedly added the words \u201cso help me God\u201d at the end. This event included a speech given outside of Federal Hall in New York City. For ten points, name this April 30, 1789 event that marked the start of the first Presidency.", "answer": "<b> inauguration</b> of George<b> Washington</b> (prompt on partial answers)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "This man agreed to a truce with England in the Treaty of Picquigny, allowing him to focus his forces against the League of the Public Weal. This man revolted against his father in the failed Praguerie and subsequently fled to Philip the Good\u2019s court. After his greatest foe was slain at Nancy, this ruler annexed Picardy. The death of Charles the Bold allowed this man to take control of Burgundy. For ten points, name this French monarch whose diplomatic cunning earned him his nickname.", "answer": "<b> Louis XI</b> (accept<b> Louis the Prudent</b> or<b> Louis</b> the (Universal)<b> Spider</b>; prompt on Louis)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "A politician from this state briefly ran for President in 2015 and condemned \u201cimmigration without assimilation\u201d as \u201cinvasion.\u201d Another politician from this state lost his 2015 bid for governor after a scandal involving him soliciting prostitutes; that man was David Vitter, who lost to a man who is now the only Democratic governor in the Deep South. For ten points, name this state that has been governed by John Bel Edwards, Bobby Jindal, and Kathleen Blanco, who served during Hurricane Katrina.", "answer": "<b> Louisiana</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "Jean Delay diagnosed one of the central figures of these events with hysterical amnesia. Former Hungarian ambassador John Montgomery helped Miklos Horthy avoid being targeted by these events. Geoffrey Lawrence and Francis Biddle were presiding figures at this event, where Robert Jackson gave an opening speech. Hjalmar Schacht was acquitted of conspiring and planning crimes against peace at this event. Rudolf Hess was among the men transported to Spandau Prison after, for ten points, what post-war trials against Nazi officials?", "answer": "<b> Nuremberg Trial</b>s (prompt on descriptive answers)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "This man died in his sleep at his summer home in Florida, The Casements. In a depiction by Puck, this man\u2019s company was shown as an octopus grabbing lawmakers and reaching for the White House. Despite his son having ordered the action, this man was criticized for the deadly force brought against protesting coal miners at his Ludlow mine. This man\u2019s corrupt business practices were exposed by muckraker Ida Tarbell, who wrote a history of his company. For ten points, name this richest ever American, the founder of Standard Oil.", "answer": "John D.<b> Rockefeller</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "A travelogue named for the scent of females from this place was written by a man whose ceramic of a female savage inspired a figure in Pablo Picasso\u2019s<em> Young Ladies of Avignon</em>. A work depicting people from this place should be viewed from right to left and was finished after its painter attempted suicide by overdosing on arsenic. In that piece about this place, each of the major groups acts alongside a blue Buddha-like idol that is meant to represent \u201cthe Beyond.\u201d The work<em> Where Do We Come From? What</em> <em>Are We? Where Are We Going?</em> was set on, for ten points, what French Polynesian island that was frequented by Paul Gauguin?", "answer": "<b> Tahiti</b> (prompt on French Polynesia before mentioned; prompt on descriptions of Pacific Islands/Oceania before \u201cthis island\u201d is read)", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Visual Fine Arts"}, {}, {"question": "For ten points, name this first Flavian emperor who ended the Year of the Four Emperors.", "answer": "<b> Vespasian</b>", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {}, {"question": "This company was criticized for deciding not to remove footage of the Lac-M\u00b4egantic disaster, one of the deadliest train derailments in Canadian history, as stock footage in one of its 2018 films. A company called \u201cQwikster\u201d was to be spunoff from this company in 2011, but CEO Reed Hastings quickly changed course. Programs like<em> Narcos</em> and the American version of<em> House of Cards</em> were produced by, for ten points, what streaming service that released<em> Bird Box</em> in 2018?", "answer": "<b> Netflix</b> BONUS:<em> Narcos</em> was a three-season drama set in Colombia about this drug kingpin, who was killed in 1993. ANSWER: Pablo<b> Escobar</b>", "metadata": "Trash - Trash"}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "<b>Ermolao Barbaro praised a book by this man but noted that it contained over five thousand pieces of scientifically inaccurate information. Upon seeing a phenomenon that</b> <b>looked \u201clike an umbrella pine,\u201d this man journeyed from Misenum to (+)</b> <b>rescue Rectina</b> <b>and Pomponianus. Although this man remarked that \u201cfortune favors the brave,\u201d his corpse was (*)</b> excavated from pumice at Stabiae. Letters to Tactius from this man\u2019s nephew detail his death during the eruption of Mount Vesuvius. For ten points, name this Roman scientist, the author of<em> Natural</em> <em>History</em>.", "answer": "<b> Pliny the Elder</b> (prompt on Pliny)", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {"question": "<b>The losing vice presidential candidate in this election year was an Oregon senator who had introduced a bill for the creation of the Grand Coulee Dam, Charles McNary. Both members of the winning ticket in this year had been interested in the philosophy of a mystic</b> <b>named Nicholas (+)</b> <b>Roerich. The winning Vice Presidential candidate in this election</b> <b>year had earlier served as Secretary of Agriculture under the incumbent and succeeded John Nance Garner. (*) </b> Wendell Wilkie lost this election, which broke the tradition of two-term presidencies. For ten points, name this election year in which FDR won, just after the start of World War II.", "answer": "US presidential election of<b> 1940</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b>These people expanded into the Volga region under the leadership of Kotrag, a leader of the \u201cBlack\u201d variant of these people. These people defeated their greatest foe at the Gates</b> <b>of Trajan after a successful defense of their capital, (+)</b> <b>Sredets. Ninety nine out of every</b> <b>hundred of these people were blinded after their defeat at the Battle of Kleidion, a sight that caused King Samuel to die of shock. The (*) </b> Byzantine emperor Basil II became known as the \u201cslayer\u201d of, for ten points, what nomadic ethnic group who later formed a country with capital Sofia?", "answer": "<b> Bulgars</b> (accept<b> Bulgarians</b>)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "<b>Gladman and his Orchestral Jazzonions are slated to perform at one event in this play, in which one title character describes Tolstoy and Lincoln as \u201csocial reformers.\u201d One of this play\u2019s title characters chastises another for (+) beating his girlfriend and ballroom dancing partner. This play\u2019s first title character demands that (*)</b> Sam stop calling him \u201cHally\u201d in favor of the title form of address. For ten points, name this play, set in the early years of Apartheid, by Athol Fugard.", "answer": "<b> Master Harold... and the Boys</b>", "metadata": "Literature - World Literature - Drama"}, {"question": "<b>Richard Fletcher took orders from this man to build the massive Lines of Torres Vedras. This man, who led the reserves at the Battle of Seringapatam in 1799, was opposed by Anthony Pohlmann, who commanded forces for the (+) Maratha ruler Raghuji Bhonsle II, at the Battle of Assaye. During the Peninsular War, this general defeated French forces at the Battle of (*) </b> Salamanca, and this man joined Gebhard von Blucher in a key victory in Belgium that led to an emperor being exiled to St. Helena. For ten points, name this British general who won the 1815 Battle of Waterloo over Napoleon.", "answer": "Arthur<b> Wellesley</b>, first Duke of<b> Wellington</b> (accept either or both underlined names)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "<b>One man with this surname negotiated with France to obtain a loan that allowed for the creation of the Bank of North America. That man with this surname headed the \u201cSecret Committee of Trade\u201d during the Second Continental Congress and is sometimes known</b> <b>as the (+)</b> <b>\u201cFinancier of the Revolution.\u201d In addition to Robert, another man with this</b> <b>\u201cFinancier of the Revolution.\u201d In addition to Robert, another man with this</b> <b>surname wrote the phrases (*)</b> <b>surname wrote the phrases (*)</b> \u201censure domestic Tranquility\u201d and \u201cform a more perfect Union\u201d at the Constitutional Convention. For ten points, give this surname shared by Robert and the author of the Preamble, Gouverneur [\u201cgovernor\u201d].", "answer": "<b> Morris</b> (accept Robert<b> Morris</b>; accept<b> Gouverneur</b> Morris)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b>This oration asks its listeners to \u201ckeep pace with the progress of the world\u201d after having\u201cresolved to pave the way for a grand peace.\u201d A copy of this oration was kept in a \u201cbank</b> <b>vault\u201d under the palace, preventing the leaders of the 15 August (+)</b> <b>coup from finding it</b> <b>before it was smuggled out in a laundry basket. This speech concedes that, despite attempts for \u201cself-preservation,\u201d a joint (*) </b> declaration from China, the United States, and the USSR was accepted, and the speaker and his country must \u201c[endure] the unendurable.\u201d For ten points, name this speech delivered by Emperor Hirohito, announcing Japan\u2019s surrender in World War II.", "answer": "<b> Jewel Voice</b> Broadcast (or<b> Gyokuon-hoso</b>; prompt on descriptive answers)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "<b>In this state, William Dixon responded to the death of John Anderson by killing over 150 members of the Wintu during the Bridge Gulch Massacre. This was the southernmost</b> <b>of two states where a chief named Captain Jack took up positions along (+)</b> <b>Tule Lake</b> <b>during the 1870\u2019s Modoc War. At the same time as the Civil War, a group of this state\u2019s namesake volunteers fought in this state\u2019s (*)</b> Owens Valley Indian War. For ten points, name this state where the Pomo were killed in the 1850 Bloody Island Massacre after refusing to be forced labor during its gold rush.", "answer": "<b> California</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b>This country\u2019s military may have sabotaged its own military stockpiles at Ojhri Camp and deposed president Muhammad Janejo after he called for an inquiry. Another leader of this country promoted \u201cSharization\u201d to move towards religious rule</b> <b>after launching Operation (+)</b> <b>Fair Play to take control in 1978. That leader of this</b> <b>country, Muhammad Zia ul-Haq, was killed in a plane crash near (*)</b> Bahawalpur and controversially executed his predecessor Zulfikar Ali. For ten points, name this Islamic Republic that has been led by two members of the Bhutto family, including Benazir, who was killed in 2007 in Rawalpindi.", "answer": "<b> Pakistan</b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}], "bonuses": []}